<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//Samba-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<preface lang="ja-JP">
<title>表紙について</title>

	<para>
	この本の表紙には<quote>オフィシャルSamba-3 HOWTOとリファレンスガイド</quote>の初版の自由テーマを継続
	している。我々の前にいた人たちの動機を質問するために過去を振り返ってもよい。過去が我々に答えの義務が
	ないことを理解し、にもかかわらず、我々の前に道を切り開いた、過去に自由を守った人々への誇りと感謝の気
	持ちを感じなければならないことを考えても良い。
	</para>

	<para>
	Developments in information technology continue to move at an alarming pace. Human nature causes us
	to adopt and embrace new developments that appear to answer the needs of the moment, but that can entrap
	us at a future date. There are many examples in the short history of information technology. MS-DOS was
	seen as a tool that liberated users from the tyrany of large computer system operating costs, and that
	made possible the rapid progres we are beneficiaries of today. Yet today we are inclined to look back with
	disdain on MS-DOS as an obsolete and constraining technology that belongs are an era that is best
	forgotten.
	</para>

	<para>
	The embrace of Windows networking, Windows NT4, and MS Active Directory in more recent times, may seem
	modern and progressive today, but sooner or later something better will replace them. The current
	preoccupation with extended identity management solutions and with directories is not unexpected.
	The day will come that these too will be evaluated, and what may seem refreshing and powerful may
	be better recogized as the chilly winds of the night. To argue against progress is unthinkable,
	no matter what may lie ahead.
	</para>

	<para>
	The development of Samba is moving forwards. The changes since Samba 3.0.0 are amazing, yet many
	users would like to see more and faster progress. The benefits of recent developments can be realized
	quickly, but documentation is necessary to unlock the pandoras' box. It is our hope that this book
	will help the network administrator to rapidly deploy the new features with minimum effort. As you
	deploy and gain mileage from the new enablement, take the time to think through what may lie ahead.
	Above all, take stock of the freedom of choice that Samba provides in your world, and enjoy the new 
	potential for seamless interoperability.
	</para>

</preface>
