<samba:parameter name="rpc_daemon:DAEMON"
                 context="G"
		 type="string"
		 advanced="1" print="1"
                 xmlns:samba="http://www.samba.org/samba/DTD/samba-doc">
<description>
        <para>
	  定義されてたrpcサービスのために、分離されたデーモンを起動するか、
	  埋め込まれたコードを使うかを定義する。
	  rpc_daemonプレフィックスはその後にサーバ名と値がなければならない。
	</para>
	<para>
	Defines whether to use the embedded code or start a separate daemon
	for the defined rpc services.
	The rpc_daemon prefix must be followed by the server name, and a value.
	</para>

	<para>
	  現時点では、以下の2つが使用可能である:
		<command moreinfo="none">disabled</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">fork</command>
	</para>

	<para>
	  旧来のメソッドはsmbd中に埋め込まれた内部デーモンとして、
	  rpcサービスを動かすものであり、それゆえ、外部デーモンは
	  既定値では<emphasis>無効</emphasis>になっている。
	</para>

	<para>
	  <emphasis>fork</emphasis>オプションを選ぶと、この方法で設定された
	  各デーモン用に分離されたプロセスを、sambaはフォークする。各デーモンは、
	  複数のsmbdからのリクエストを処理する為に使われる、複数の子プロセスを
	  順番にフォークする(エンドポイントマッパが有効な場合)。
	  名前付きパイプ上で発生し、そこで指定されたパイプを要求するsmbdとの
	  通信は、外部デーモンにフォワードされる(<smbconfoption name="rpc_server"/>
	  を参照のこと)。
	</para>
	<para>
	Choosing the <emphasis>fork</emphasis> option will cause samba to fork
	a separate proces for each daemon configured this way. Each daemon may
	in turn fork a number of children used to handle requests from multiple
	smbds and direct tcp/ip connections (if the Endpoint Mapper is
	enabled). Communication with smbd happens over named pipes and require
	that said pipes are forward to the external daemon (see <smbconfoption
	name="rpc_server"/>).
	</para>

	<para>
	  フォークされたRPCデーモンは接続を扱うために動的に子プロセスをフォーク
	  する事をサポートする。どのくらい子プロセスを作るか、どのくらい早く
	  それらをフォークするか、また、どのくらい各子プロセスにクライアントを
	  同時に取り扱うかについて、ヒューリスティックな方法は、デーモンの後に
	  名前が付けられたparametricalオプションによって定義される。
	  現時点では以下の5つのオプションがある。
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_min_children</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_max_children</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_spawn_rate</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_max_allowed_clients</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_child_min_life</command>

		上記のオプションの1つを設定するためには以下の方法を使う:
	<programlisting>
	damonname:prefork_min_children = 5
	</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	Forked RPC Daemons support dynamically forking children to handle
	connections. The heuristics about how many children to keep around and
	how fast to allow them to fork and also how many clients each child is
	allowed to handle concurrently is defined by parametrical options named
	after the daemon.
	Five options are currently supported:
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_min_children</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_max_children</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_spawn_rate</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_max_allowed_clients</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">prefork_child_min_life</command>

	To set one of these options use the follwing syntax:
	<programlisting>
	damonname:prefork_min_children = 5
	</programlisting>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Sambaはspoolssとlsarpc/lsass, netlogonとsamr pipes用に分離されたデーモンを
	  含む。現在、3つのデーモンが有効でそれらは以下の通りである:
		<command moreinfo="none">epmd</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">lsasd</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">spoolssd</command>
	例:
	<programlisting>
	rpc_daemon:spoolssd = fork
	</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	Samba includes separate daemons for spoolss and the lsarpc/lsass,
	netlogon and samr pipes. Currently three daemons are available and they
	are called:
		<command moreinfo="none">epmd</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">lsasd</command>
		<command moreinfo="none">spoolssd</command>
	Example:
	<programlisting>
	rpc_daemon:spoolssd = fork
	</programlisting>
	</para>
</description>

<value type="default">disabled</value>
</samba:parameter>
